you probably heard the claim that to
succeed at trading you should keep
things simple and not over complicate
things on face value this is true but
it's also incredibly misleading and it's
the cause of failure for many beginners
let me explain so a woman walks into a
Parisian Cafe and notices a man sitting
at a table scribbling onto his napkin as
the waiter brings over his coffee he
Chucks the napkin to the side and at
that moment the woman realizes she's
been watching Pablo Picasso
she's a struck and after debating with
herself for a moment she builds up the
confidence to go and speak to him mon
Picasso she says I love your work could
I possibly have that little drawing
you've done on the napkin Picasso looks
up at her excited face and replies yes
of course Madame that will be 10,000
Franks her face transforms into outrage
10,000 Franks but only took you 30
seconds to draw no my dear he replies
it's taken me 40 years
now whether or not that story is true I
doubt it it has an important meaning
particularly for someone learning to
trade a master of their craft can often
make things look quick and simple an
amateur might think that it must be easy
to replicate and then set how to do that
that would imply the path to trading
success looks like this and this is
where most beginners go wrong they're
doing the equivalent of looking at
Picasso's simple sketch and thinking
that that's what they need to achieve to
be a legendary artist but if we take a
look at the bull a famous piece of art
by Picasso we see a different process
and this is also reflected in the
progression of Picasso's style over the
years we can see it going from a complex
approach to a more simple one so what's
this got to do with trading it gives us
an insight into the route towards
Mastery instead of being linear like
this chart it looks more like this as
you learn you progress upwards along the
curve you take on New Concepts new
techniques new knowledge which increases
the complexity of what you're doing at
the beginning you might only pay
attention to a few simple things but as
you progress you have many different
things to mentally process at the same
time it feels complex and difficult at
some point you'll reach the top of the
curve where you experience Peak
complexity at this point you may be able
to achieve positive results but it takes
a lot of work and it feels complicated
now most people give up long before they
reach that point but those who do reach
it will usually stop developing once
they get there they'll feel like they
know everything they need to and they'll
turn their attention to using the skill
rather than developing it further when
people reach this point we can say that
they are satisficed that's a funny term
that you might have encountered if
you've ever studied economics it's a
portmanto of satisfy and suffice and
could be Loosely translated to mean good
enough in other words people stop when
they feel they've reached a level that's
good enough they don't strive to go
further but going Beyond good enough is
where all the great things happen it's
how you experience a flow State it's how
you build expertise and Achieve Mastery
is how you become a high performer if we
think about the journey up the curve
this is defined by adding more things to
what we already know or do we're
increasing the level of complexity but
the journey down the curve is all about
subtracting we're achieving what lady
clot describes in his book subtract as
post satisficed less however this takes
a huge amount of effort it's like the
famous quote by blae Pascal which is
famously misattributed to other people
if I had more time I would have written
a shorter letter with my trading I do
mostly try to keep things very simple it
may even appear in some situations to be
quite basic on face value but the
Simplicity High a great deal of
complexity and if you want to know more
about how I trade and the most important
aspects that I believe Traders need to
focus on check out the training link
down below where I walk you through all
of the logic of it you see it's by
understanding and knowing the complexity
that you'll know what's needed and what
can be removed in a particular situation
Simplicity begins with knowledge
Simplicity is the ultimate
sophistication Leonardo da Vinci the
approach might look simple but the
thought process that leads to that point
relies on years of development and
understanding it's just like Picasso's
bull it's by knowing all the intricate
details that he can boil something down
to its Essence in just a few elegant
pencil Strokes in fact this also relates
to what we discover by looking at brain
research this was shown in a study on
people learning to play Tetris when they
first started large parts of their brain
lit up displaying the learning process
that was taking place this is when their
brain exerted the most energy and
everything felt effortful then once they
mastered the actions that they needed to
take their movements became more
habitual and brain activity in the
cortex died down the brain was drawing
less glucose and less oxygen and their
reactions increased rapidly they were
essentially moving from conscious
incompetence to conscious competence and
finally to unconscious competence their
brains were making recurring actions
habitual so you could say based on brain
research that we spend a lot more time
thinking when we're not good at an
activity which is the opposite of what
most people think and this is exactly
what happens when you're developing as a
Trader as you add more complexity
Everything feels effortful and you have
to think through everything you're doing
but when you achieve posts satisficed
Mastery your brain can automatically
focus on what's important sometimes even
without you realizing and Lead You
towards a simple approach but when a
beginner tries to direct IR L imitate
the Simplicity they fail miserably
they're misled by the simple output and
don't have the knowledge skills or
understanding to process the complexity
that's led to that they're seeing the
swan gliding gracefully over the water
but missing all the kicking that's
happening underneath so although it may
be your end goal to gracefully trade the
markets with sophisticated Simplicity
the journey to that point is not linear
to achieve Simplicity meaning ful
Simplicity you need to begin with
complexity and only then can you put the
effort into post satisfice less so with
all of that being said what does all of
this mean specifically for your trading
well there are two main points I want
you to take away here the first is that
you should still well clear of focusing
on trading methods that offer you
complete Simplicity things where you
just have to memorize some rules
strategies or patterns rather than
deeply understanding the logic behind
what you're doing for example there's
been a recent Resurgence in mechanical
rules trading where you completely
remove the aspect of discretion or
market knowledge likewise there are
other methods where you just have to
memorize or identify where to place a
level or a Zone without understanding
why it's there and what the rest of the
market activity is revealing for you you
know it might be that eventually your
trading does reach a point where you can
rely on a simple approach with simple
rules but for that to succeed it's
likely to be due to your brain
processing information like a complex
algorithm to create that simple output
it's called implicit knowledge you might
not even notice that you're doing it so
instead while you're developing you
should be focusing your time on learning
as much as you can about the markets
themselves you should understand how the
markets operate why prices do or don't
move like what's actually happening what
are the mechanics behind this and The
Logical basis behind everything you're
doing don't just take things on face
value understand the logic understand if
it's meaningful explore different
methods and learn new things but make
sure you're focusing on the logic of the
aspects that you're learning so that you
can determine if they're meaningful or
not most things out there are a complete
waste of your time and they're just
surface level nonsense of course who
wouldn't be tempted by simple secret
rules that lead you to profits that
sounds great I can see why people get
tempted by that but the truth is
successful trading comes from logic and
critical thinking not from rot memory
trading is a skill not something to be
memorized the second point is about what
you choose to compare your progress to
it's inevitable that if your journey
involves increasing complexity before
you start simplifying you're going to
reach a point where your trading feels a
lot more complicated and messy than
someone who's genuinely succeeding at a
later point in their Journey but you
shouldn't take this as a sign that
you're on the wrong track it simply
means that you haven't progressed to
that stage yet but you'll get there
eventually hopefully provides that
you're learning the right things in the
right way let me make this clear I'm not
saying that you have to over complicate
things to succeed at trading we've all
seen those charts that look an absolute
mess with indicators and lines all over
the place I'm not encouraging you to do
that we don't want to add complexity for
the sake of it I'm saying that before
you can achieve meaningful Simplicity
it's necessary to understand a certain
amount of complexity so that you know
what's essential and what can be removed
in any particular situation and it won't
always be the same things just like with
any other skill to be absolutely blunt
the people who promote always keeping
trading really simple from when you
start learning till when you're an
expert are either trying to sell
something by making it sound really easy
and simple to do they're giving advice
based on survivorship bias because it
luckily worked out for them they're not
realizing that the complexity they
experienced while they were learning
gave them the implicit know to be able
to achieve their current Simplicity or
it's just that they can't be bothered to
learn about the markets deeply
themselves so they argue that it's not
necessary to everyone else simply to
excuse their own laziness and make them
feel better about it just saying and if
you want to understand more about how
all of this relates to the Psychology
and Neuroscience of learning to trade
and why trading is such a frustrating
skill to learn more so than other skills
then check out this video next